Pablo Francisco Mendoza Vargas

pm3179@columbia.edu

736 Riverside Drive, New York, NY 10031

https://pfmv2023.netlify.app/

SUMMARY

Bilingual professional with strong analytical and problem-solving skills. Proficient in R, Python, SQL, Spark, and JavaScript. Over six years' experience in data modeling and project management in a Fortune 500 company. Experienced at addressing diverse data processing and analysis requirements. Valedictorian. Awarded with "Excellence PRIMA AFP" in 2011, the top award for academic excellence in the country, by GRUPO CREDITO, the leading Finance Corporation in Peru.

CORE COMPETENCIES

Technology. Statistical Programming (R / Python). Data Science (Scikit-Learn)

Database & Software. Project Management Experience. Machine Learning.

EDUCATION

Columbia University, New York, NY

Major: Computer and Information Sciences - MS in Applied Analytics - STEM; GPA 3.98

December 2023

• Relevant Coursework: Machine Learning, Python for Data Analysis, Research Design, Applied Analytics Frameworks & Methods I-II, Strategy and Analytics, Storytelling with Data, Managing Data.

San Ignacio de Loyola University, Lima, PERU

Major: Commercial Management and Marketing - MS in Management; GPA 3.86

December 2013

Relevant Coursework: Information Technology, Quantitative Business Methods.

Peruvian University of Applied Sciences, Lima, PERU

Major: Industrial Engineering - BSc in Industrial Engineering; GPA 3.47

July 2011

 Relevant Coursework: Algorithms, Numeric Methods, Operations Research, Graphic Programming and Databases, IT for Engineers, Information Systems, Statistics and Probabilities, Applied Statistics, Simulation Systems, Mathematical Analysis I, II, III, IV.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Regeneron - Graduate Intern; New York, USA

May 2023 - Present

- Collaborated with the portfolio management team to integrate data science solutions into existing applications.
- Applied NLP techniques such as named entity recognition (NER), relationship extraction, and document classification.
- Build an interactive interface using HTML, CSS, and JavaScript to elevate the user experience.
- Applied data science programming to discern significant patterns in clinical trials through data mining, pattern recognition techniques (including clustering and decision trees), and predictive analytics (using scikit-learn).

The University of Arizona - Global Lecturer; Lima, PERU

March 2020 - July 2022

- Deterministic Operations Research: Coached students on the working knowledge of three operations research techniques linear programming, network models and integer programming.
- Probabilistic Models in Operations Research: Directed students in five units: probabilistic decision analysis, stochastic processes, markov chains, queueing theory, and stochastic inventory models.

Peruvian University of Applied Sciences - Full Time Lecturer; Lima, PERU

March 2018 - July 2022

- Discrete System Simulation: Trained students in the use of algorithms for automated reasoning and data processing. Published 4 science papers in international journals.
- Applied Research Project II: Coached students in utilizing quantitative mathematics and scientific principles to identify goals and assess the suitability of qualitative research in over fifty projects.

America Movil - New Projects Coordinator; Lima, PERU

November 2013 - February 2018

- Managed a cross-disciplinary team to design and implement data-driven, customized products for the TOP 1000 companies in Peru.
 This encompassed spearheading the design of the front end of the products and collaborating with programmers to develop the back end, guaranteeing smooth integration and optimal functionality.
- Leaded project management and data-driven product design for one of the top five B2B clients, overseeing the creation of product features and drafting requirement documents for engineers and DevOps. Facilitated collaborative conversations between vendors and clients to enable capabilities and drive successful implementation. Developed a customized technological solution to fulfill the client's communication requirements.

- Apply data mining techniques and the k-means clustering algorithm for customer segmentation, leveraging data analytics to optimize marketing strategies. This procedure resulted in a 25% surge in sales leads within six months.
- Managed executive-level reporting, converting analytics insights into practical data findings and business recommendations for senior management. This directly bolstered B2B sales promotion strategies, resulting in a significant increase in cross-selling customer base from 28% to 42%.
- Automatize reporting procedures through the creation of web interfaces and backend data structuring. Successfully automated 30% of the area's data reports, resulting in a weekly time savings of 12 hours previously spent on manual work.
- Create and execute different A/B tests on marketing campaigns to discover practical insights and develop effective strategies.
- Conducted extensive data analysis and data mining to identify and rectify intricate data patterns and inconsistencies, thereby
 ensuring the integrity of the data.

America Movil - Junior Business Analyst; Lima, PERU

January 2012 - June 2012

- Optimize the data pipeline and automate report generation by improving query performance, resulting in reduced execution time and simplified output structure. This streamlined process enabled the production of 8 weekly reports and analytical metrics using business intelligence data in the B2B market.
- Implemented various Machine Learning models, including Regression analysis, Decision Tree, and Random Forest, to optimize the forecast of device requirements. This implementation resulted in a 40% reduction in stock shortages.
- Collaborated with executives and department heads to deploy advanced analytics data modeling systems, fostering a data-driven culture within the organization. Utilized data analytics to re-engineer the sales process, identifying standardization opportunities and achieving a 17% reduction in sales process time.
- Awarded for the development of the best automatization process in 2012 at America Movil Peru, leading the project "Automatization of the migration process from prepaid to postpaid".

America Movil - Marketing Intern; Lima, PERU

July 2010 - December 2011

- Developed interactive Tableau dashboards for executives, facilitating access and analysis of critical data. These purpose-built dashboards reported on three essential performance indicators: sales, products, and customer segmentation.
- Evaluated cost-benefit of the marketing strategies of two sales chanels: distributors and digital.

LEADERSHIP EXPERIENCE AND ACTIVITIES

Regeneron - NEW YORK, USA

May 2023 - Present

- Regeneron for Good: Project Leader.
- RADS Regeneron Analyst and Data Scientist.

Columbia University - NEW YORK, USA

Sep 2022 - Present

- Columbia Data Science Society V.P. Operations.
- Columbia-Barnard Undergrad Computer and Data Science Research Fair Speaker.
- 2023 Columbia Data Science Hackathon Organizer.
- Columbia Athletics Provided tutoring in Environmental Economics to high-performance athletes, guiding them in utilizing Python and R for their research projects.

HONORS

• "Excellence PRIMA AFP" scholar.

2011.

San Ignacio de Loyola University Graduate Scholarship.

Jan 2012 - Dec 2013.

• Peruvian University of Applied Sciences Honors Scholarship.

Jan 2008 - Aug 2011.

OTHER CREDENTIALS

Rice University: Global Financial Markets and Instruments Certification.

The British Council in Peru: Academic Teaching Excellence Certificate.